<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
  schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Priapeia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Thibault Clérice</publisher>
                <!-- This data has been produced in the context of Thibault's
                    Clérice's PhD at the University of Lyon 3 and under contract at the École Nationale des Chartes -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>SPORTIVE EPIGRAMS ON PRIAPUS</title>
                    <title>by divers poets in English verse and prose</title>
                    <editor role="editor"><name>Smithers</name>, <forename>Leonard <abbr>C.</abbr></forename></editor>
                    <editor role="editor"><roleName>Sir</roleName> <name>Burton</name>, <forename>Richard</forename></editor>
                    <pubPlace>Leipzig</pubPlace>
                    <date>1890</date>
                </bibl>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Sacred Text</title>
                    <date>2000</date>
                    <ref>http://www.sacred-texts.com/cla/priap/priapeia.htm</ref>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="poem" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts poem</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2017-06-12" who="Thibault Clérice">Converted to EpiDoc/CapiTainS</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
            <div type="edition" n="" xml:lang="eng">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="1"><p>Do thou, who art about to read these wanton sallies of careless verse, lay aside the brow befitting Latium.<note type="footnote"> The poet commemorates the three goddesses, Diana, Vesta and Minerva, whose perpetual virginity knew no man. 'Callimachus, in a Hymn to this Goddess [Diana</note> Not Phoebus's sister, not Vesta in her sanctuary, nor that Goddess sprung from her father's brain,<note type="footnote"/> dwells here: but the ruddy Protector of our Gardens, larger membered than is usual, and who has his groin covered by no garment. Therefore, either spread thy tunic over that part which 'tis meet to conceal; or with the same eyes that thou lookest upon it, peruse these.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="2"><p>For pastime, and with little care, have I written these verses, thee attesting,<note type="footnote"> Possibly with a punning allusion to testicles.</note> O Priapus--verses worthy a garden,<note type="footnote"> A double entendre intended to be conveyed by the word 'garden'.</note> not a little book! Nor have I, as poets are wont, invoked the Muses to this unvirginal spot. For I had neither mind nor heart for the emprise, to bring the chaste sisters, the chorus of Pïérides, to the mentule<note type="footnote"> The male member--mentula.</note> of Priapus. Therefore, whatever it is I have jotted in an idle hour on the walls of thy temple, take it in good part, I pray thee.</p></div>
                
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="3"><p>Lalage dedicates a votive offering to the God of the standing prickle, bringing pictures from the shameless books of Elephantis, and begs him to try and imitate with her all the different coitions of the painted figures.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="4"><p>Hereunder is written in two verses the condition which Priapus is said to have made with a boy:</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="5"><p>Though I am, as you see, a wooden Priapus, with wooden reaping-hook and a wooden penis; yet I will seize thee, and when thou art caught [my girl], I will enjoy thee. And the whole of this, large though it be, and stiffer than twisted cord, than the string of the lyre, I will surely bury in thee to thy seventh rib.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="6"><p>Whenever I speak, one word slips me; for, talking with a lisp, I always say instead of praedico, paedico!<note type="footnote"> Instead of saying 'praedico', meaning 'I warn you not to trespass', he lisps and says 'paedico', meaning 'I am sodomising you'.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="7"><p>Go far hence, ye virtuous wives, 'tis unseemly for you to read lewd verses.<note type="footnote"> The obscene inscriptions scrawled on the base of his statue.</note> They care not an as [for my words],<note type="footnote"> A Roman copper coin of small value.</note> and straightway approach. Verily these matrons are sensible, and look joyfully, too, on the well-grown mentule.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="8"><p>Why are my privy parts without vesture? you demand. I ask why no God conceals his emblem? The Lord of the World [Jupiter] has his thunderbolt, and holds it unconcealed; nor is a covered trident given to the God of the Sea [Neptune]. Mars does not secrete the sword by whose means he prevails; nor does Pallas's spear lie hid in the warm bosom of her robe. Is Phoebus ashamed to carry his golden arrows? Is Diana wont to bear her quiver secretly? Does Alcides conceal the strength of his knotted club? Has the winged God [Mercury] his caduceus under his tunic? Who has seen Bacchus draw his garment over the slender thyrsus; or thee, O Love, with hidden torch? Nor should it be a reproach to me that my mentule is always uncovered. For if this spear be wanting to me, I am weaponless.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="9"><p>Why, most foolish girl, do you laugh? Neither Praxiteles<note type="footnote"> Praxiteles, according to Pliny, lived in the time of Pompeius: his statue of Venus was very famous.</note> nor Scopas<note type="footnote"> Scopas was a celebrated sculptor in marble and carved in relief on the Mausoleum.</note> has given me shape, nor have I been perfected by the hand of Phidias;<note type="footnote"> Phidias was a renowned ivory sculptor.</note> but a bailiff carved me from a shapeless log, and said to me, 'You are Priapus!'<note type="footnote"> The statue was so badly carved that the sculptor had to explain what his work was intended to represent.</note> Yet you gaze at me, and laugh repeatedly. Doubtless it seems to you a droll thing--the 'column' standing upright from my groin.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="10"><p>Take heed lest thou art caught. If I do seize thee, nor with my club will I belabour thee, nor cruel wounds with the curved sickle will inflict on thee. Thrust into by my twelve-inch I pole, thou shalt be so stretched that thou wilt drink thy anus never had any wrinkles.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="11"><p>A certain hag, more aged than the mother [Hecuba] of Hector (the sister, I opine, of the Cumaean Sibyl), old as thou whom Theseus when he came back home found lying in the grave, often comes hither with tottering steps, and lifting her shrivelled hands to the stars, begs that she may not lack the mentule. In yesterday's fight too, while praying, she spat out one of her three teeth. Take it far away, I say, and bid it he concealed under thy tattered tunic and thy scarlet stole, as 'tis its custom; let it shun the fight of thy meagre jaws, which, thy hairy nose in the air, gape with a chasm so foul and enormous that you would. think an Epicurean was yawning.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="12"><p>I warn thee, my lad, thou wilt be sodomised; thee, my girl, I shall futter;<note type="footnote"> Futuere. Used frequently by Martial. Derived from fundo, to pour out (the semen).</note> for the thief who is bearded, a third punishment<note type="footnote"> Tertia poene in the Latin original meaning irrumation, or coition with the mouth.</note> remains.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="13"><p>Hither, hither, whoever thou art, to the venerable sanctuary of the lecherous God, nor think to be turned away. And if a girl were with thee in the night, 'tis no reason why thou shouldst fear to approach my altar; though it is otherwise with the stem Gods above.<note type="footnote"> The ancients thought that those defiled by carnal coition generally were precluded from worship of the gods until they had been purified by bathing.</note> I am a good-for-naught, a paltry rustic deity of scant culture. I stand in the open air, my modesty thrust aside, My bollocks exposed to view. Therefore, 'tis permitted to enter hither all who will, besmirched with the black filth of the stews.<note type="footnote"> In the stews, they had lamps hanging, on the back part of which was expressed, hieroglyphically, to whom they were dedicated. Many of these lamps bore phallic emblems: I have seen one on the upper part of which was a sculpture representing Leda in the act of coition with the swan. The Satyricon of Petronius Arbiter and the Satires of Juvenal and Horace all speak of the Roman brothels, which were constructed in the form of a gallery along which were ranged, on each side like a nunnery, a number of contiguous cells or chambers. Over the door of each of these was posted a bill with the price and name of the tenant, who stood at the entrance soliciting the preferences of the visitors.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="14"><p>He who shall plunder with dishonest hand the little field committed to my charge, shall feel me to be no eunuch<note type="footnote"> Martial and Juvenal have many references to eunuchism and the use to which the Roman ladies put these castratos, who were of various kinds: castrati (castare, meaning to cut oft)--those who had lost both penis and testicles; spadones (either spata, a Gallic word meaning a razor, or Spada, a Persian village where the operation of eunuchism is performed)--those who still retained the penis; thlibiae (from the Greek meaning to rub with hemlock, etc.)--those whose testicles had been extracted by compression; thliasiae (from the Greek meaning to crush); cremaster (so called from the destruction of the muscle, cremaster, by which the testicle is suspended or drawn up or compressed in the act of coition); and bagoas. The subject scarcely calls for extended notice in this work, but I would refer those interested in the subject to The Book of the Thousand Nights and a Night, translated by Sir Richard F. Burton.</note> in this lonely place among the bushes. Here, perhaps, he will say this to himself, 'None will know that I have been thrust through.'<note type="footnote"> Praecidere (literally meaning to cut off). Here means to cut through the bowels. It has a similar meaning in Juvenal--'to run against yesterday's supper'. Like expressions are billas dividere, 'to divide the bowels', and cacare mentulam, 'to defile the mentule with ordure'.</note> He will be mistaken; that cause will be sustained by 'weighty' witnesses!<note type="footnote"> In the original, magnis testibus, meaning trustworthy witness; and, by a play upon words, large testicles.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="15"><p>As the apples with which Hippomenes raped the daughter of Schoeneus;<note type="footnote"> Referring to the story of the race between Hippomenes and Atalanta, and how the crafty lover tricked the damsel into defeat by the three gold apples.</note> for which the garden of the Hesperides was renowned; which one may imagine Nausicaa<note type="footnote"> Nausicaa was the daughter of Alcinous, king of Phaeacia, whose pleasure demensnes and luxuriousness became a proverb.</note> often carrying in her teeming lap as she walked in her father's domains; as was that apple graced by the words of Acontius, which, read aloud [by Cydippe], pledged the maiden to this ardent lover<note type="footnote"> The story is very prettily told by Aristaenetus. The words on the apple were--'I swear to thee inviolably, by the mystic rites of Diana, that I will join myself to thee as thy companion and will become thy bride.' According to Vossius the gift of an apple was equivalent to a promise of the last favour. The Emperor Theodosius caused Paulinus to be murdered for receiving an apple from his empress.</note>--such are those which the boy-owner of a small but fertile field has placed on thy sacrificial table, O naked Priapus.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="16"><p>What hast thou to do with me, thou meddlesome watchman? why dost thou hinder the thief from coming to me? Let him approach: he will return more 'open</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="17"><p>The greatest advantage in my penis is this, that no woman can be [too] roomy<note type="footnote"> A popular theme of the poets. From Scioppius, 'However loose her coynte may be I will zealously fill it.' And from Martial against Lydia--'Me roomy Lydia's private parts surpassThe lusty dray horse' elephantine arse;Wide as the schoolboy's ringing iron hoop;Vast as the ring the agile riders stoopAnd leap through neatly, touching not the side,As round and round the dusty course they ride;Capacious as some old and well-worn shoe,That's trudged the muddy streets since first 'twas new;Stretched like the net the crafty fowler holds;And drapery as a curtain's heavy folds;Loose as the bracelet gemmed with green and scarlet,That mocks the arm of some consumptive harlot;Slack as a feather bed without the feathers;And baggy as some ostler's well-used leathers;Relaxed and hanging like the skinny coatThat shields the vulture's foul and flabby throat.'Tis said, while bathing once we trod love's path,I know not, but I seemed to fuck the bath.A somewhat similar person was the provident wife in the poem of "The Sutler', who when her husband was robbed of his horses and waggon and all his goods by a party of the enemy's forces, consoled him as follows--'No matter,' she said, and look'd with a smile,'I did the damn'd party, in some sort, beguile;'Then drew out a purse twice as big as your fist,'Tho' they search'd me,' said she, 'this treasure they missed;Then prithee, be cheerful.' This gave him new life,He wept, and he laugh'd, and he ogl'd his wife,And leering upon her, said, 'Tell me, my dear,Where was it you hid the purse I see here?'She smil'd on her spouse, then laugh'd in his face,'I hid it,' said she, 'in a certain place,With which you're acquainted! He said, 'My dear life,I see you're a careful and provident wife;You've done very well, but you'd had more to brag on,If you there had conceal'd the horses and waggon.'</note> for me.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="18"><p>Will Telethusa, the posture-dancer, who heaves up her haunches, denuded of tunic, more gracefully and higher than her bosom,<note type="footnote"> The posture alluded to is that attitude in coition in which the man lies supine, whilst the woman mounts on him and provokes the orgasm by her movements.</note> ever, with undulating loins,<note type="footnote"> In the original Latin, flucto, referring here to the wave-like motion of the loins during congress.</note> wriggle her thighs<note type="footnote"> In the original Latin, crisso, meaning the buckings and wrigglings of a woman's thighs and haunches during congress.</note> for thee in such wise as not only to excite thy desires, O Priapus, but even those of the stepson of Phaedra?</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="19"><p>Jove controls the thunderbolts; the trident is Neptune's weapon; Mars is mighty by the sword; thine, Minerva, is the spear. Bacchus fights his battles with a bundle of thyrsi; the bolt, we are told, is shot by Apollo's hand. Hercules' invincible right arm is equipped with a club; but a mentule at full stretch makes me appalling</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="20"><p>All my wealth have I lost; be propitious when I ask thee, nor betray me, Priapus, by word or deed. Tell it to none, that these home-grown apples, which I have placed on thy altar, are from the Sacred Way</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="21"><p>If a woman, man, or boy, thieve from me, let her coynte, his mouth, the latter's buttocks, be submitted [to my mentule].</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="22"><p>Whoever shall herein pluck a violet or a rose, or pilfer vegetables or unbought apples, I pray that in the absence of both woman and boy he may continually burst with that rigid tension which you see in me, and that his mentule may in vain beat throbbing on his navel</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="23"><p>The steward has bidden me, the protector of this fertile garden, have a care of the place committed to my charge. Thou, O thief, shalt be punished; thou mayst be enraged, and say, 'On account of a cabbage am I to endure this? On account of a cabbage?'<note type="footnote"> Some read prope, meaning near--'Am I to be sodomised near a cabbage?' instead of propter, meaning on account of. Because, it is presumed, the thief thought a cabbage plot too open a space for such a punishment.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="24"><p>This staff of office, which, severed from the tree, can now shoot forth no verdure; sceptre, which pathic maidens crave, and some kings love to hold; to which patrician<note type="footnote"> 'Patrician' and 'notorious' are alternative renderings of 'the Latin word oscula.</note> paederasts give kisses; shall go right into the very bowels of the thief, as far as the hair and the bag of balls.<note type="footnote"> The whole of Priapus's member to the very hair of the pudendum and the scrotum would be thrust into the thief.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="25"><p>Hither! ye Romans' Either lop off my seminal member, which the neighbouring women, ever itching with desire, exhaust the whole night through<note type="footnote"> Either the women exhausted Priapus with their mouths or by riding upon him.</note>--more lecherous than sparrows in the spring<note type="footnote"> Scioppius recounts having seen sparrows in spring copulate so many times in succession that, when trying to fly away, they fell to the ground exhausted.</note>--or I shall be ruptured (for where is the limit of their lust?), nor will ye have a Priapus. Ye see that I am spent with venery, jaded, thin and pale, who once, ruddy and vigorous, used to thrust through the stoutest thieves. My strength has faded me; and, wretched with coughing, I spit out noxious saliva.<note type="footnote"> In connection with this epigram may be mentioned the practice of tribadism with phalli amongst the Roman ladies. Giraldus tells us that the Lesbian women used dildoes made of glass, ivory, gold and silken stuffs and linen to satisfy their lechery. Suidas and Aristophanes speak of the use by Milesian women of a leathern penis succedaneum, called olisbos. Martial and Suetonius hint at the use of a snake for a similar purpose. Petronius makes Oenothea introduce a leathern fascinum, smeared with oil, pepper and crushed nettle seeds, into the anus of Encolpius as an aphrodisiac.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="26"><p>Quinctia, the people's darling, renowned in the Great Circus, cunning to flirt her tremulous buttocks to and fro, the cymbals and the castanet, the weapons of wantonness,<note type="footnote"> So called because the songs and dances to which the cymbals and castanets were accompaniments were of a loose and wanton character, inciting the spectators to venery.</note> dedicates to Priapus, and the tambour, struck by the hand towards her drawn. And she prays for them, that she may always find favour with her spectators; and that her crowd of admirers may be 'rigid'<note type="footnote"> This was looked on as a mark of the dancer's success in arousing the spectators' passions by her lascivious movements and postures.</note>, after the manner of the god.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="27"><p>Thou who wickedly designest, and scarce forbearest from robbing my garden, shall be sodomised with my twelve-inch fascinum [phallus]. But if so severe and unpleasant a punishment shall not avail., I will strike higher</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="28"><p>May I die,<note type="footnote"> A favourite formula of oath amongst the Romans.</note> Priapus, if I do not blush to make use of lewd and impure words; but when you, a deity without shame, display to me your balls in all openness, I must call a tool a tool, a coynte a coynte.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="29"><p>Priapus, terrific with thy sickle and thy greater part, tell me, prithee, which is the way to the fountain?<note type="footnote"> Scaliger says that figures of Priapus and of Mercury were placed at crossroads, with rods in their hands, pointing out the way to fountains. 'The figure of Hermes had, like that of Priapus, a long and massive phallus; I have seen them in a cardinal's palace at Rome; and another proof is the saying of the philosophers, who, deriding the gluttony and lust of the youths, compared them to tois ermais [statues of Mercury</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="30"><p>Haste thee through these vines, for if thou hast plucked off their clustering grapes, guest! thou wilt take the water for another purpose</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="31"><p>So long as thou snatchest nothing from me with audacious hand, thou mayst be chaster than Vesta herself. But, if thou dost, these belly-weapons of mine will so stretch thee that thou wilt be able to slip through thy own anus.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="32"><p>Girl, more meagre than dried grapes,<note type="footnote"> This is reminiscent of an epigram by Catullus against Furius, in which he describes him as having a body more dried than horn by extreme poverty; adding, 'Sweat, saliva, mucus and nasal snivelling, all these are absent from thee. Add to this cleanliness the still greater cleanliness that thy buttocks are purer than a salt-cellar. Thou does not cack ten times in the whole of the year, and then it is harder than a bean or than pebbles, so that if thou rubbest and crumblest it in thy hands thou canst never dirty a finger.'</note> more dusky-white than boxwood or unsullied wax; who makes the ants congregated on her body and members seem corpulent; whose bowels the Etruscan soothsayer could without opening see through the skin; who, like pumice, has no sap, insomuch as no one has seen her sputter; who, physicians think, has sand for blood, and in her veins sawdust--[this girl] is wont to come to me in the night, and approaches me, wan, attenuate and ghostlike, whilst I, as an insular iron-worker scrapes,<note type="footnote"> Islands abound in metals, hence convicts in ancient times were transported to work on them.</note> seem to be rubbing in the horn of a lantern.<note type="footnote"> Here used in a jocular comparison of the girl's parts with the horn of a lantern for hardness and dryness in coition.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="33"><p>Of old, the Priapi enjoyed the Naiads and Dryads, and there was the wherewithal to cause the swollen vein of the God to droop. Now there is naught of this; moreover, I am so full of desire that I think the whole of the Nymphs have perished. 'Tis doubtless an unseemly thing to do, but lest I burst with the excessive tension [of my member], my hand, the sickle laid aside, shall become my mistress</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="34"><p>At a sacrifice made to the God of Lechery, a girl was cheaply hired as sufficient for the wants of the common weal, who as many men she spent in a single night, dedicates to thee so many willow-wood pokers.<note type="footnote"> In the original Latin verpa, meaning the virile member. So called from its similarity in shape to the instrument used in scouring furnace fires. The damsel laid on the altar of Priapus, as ex-votos, a quantity of wooden members equal in number to the men with whom she had had connection in a single night. This seems to have been a customary practice amongst the lower classes of women.Juvenal relates how the Empress Messalina was accustomed in disguise to visit a brothel at night, and borrowing her cell from Lycisca, one of the courtesans, to show such capability for the work that she exhausted all who cared to visit her, and returned to the palace in the early morning, still raging with unsatisfied lust. It is said that within twenty hours she surpassed the above-named courtesan by twenty-five 'rides'.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="35"><p>Thou shalt be bardashed,<note type="footnote"> Bardache, meaning a catamite. Italian bardascia, from the Arabic baradaj, a captive, a slave. The old English was ingle or yngle (a bardachio, a catamite, a boy kept for sodomy). In Latin Bulgarus means a Bulgarian or a heretic, from which our vulgar modern word 'bugger' is derived, as is the Italian bugiardo and the French bougre.</note> thief, for the first theft; and if twice caught, I will irrumate thee. But if thou shalt attempt a third theft, that thou mayst suffer penalties twain, I will both sodomise and irrumate thee.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="36"><p>We have each distinguishing features in the formation of our bodies: in Phoebus 'tis luxuriant locks, in Hercules muscular power; and the effeminate Bacchus has the figure of a girl. Minerva's eye is light in colour, Venus's prettily blinking. You see the forehead of the Arcadian Fauns rubicund with colour. The messenger of the gods, [Mercury] has shapely feet, the guardian of Lemnos walks with an uneven step [the lame Vulcan] and Aesculapius always wears a never shaven beard. No man is more broad-chested than the warlike Mars; but if 'mid this array there remain any place for me, than Priapus no Deity hath a larger or better-hung mentule</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="37"><p>You ask why the instrument of procreation has been painted on the memorable tablet. When by accident I had bruised my penis, and wretched with suffering, dreaded the hand of the surgeon (moreover I was afraid to give the cure of my mentule to the legitimate and almighty gods, such as Phoebus, for instance, and Phoebus's son),<note type="footnote"> Phoebus was the god of the healing art. Aesculapius was his son.</note> 'Help, O Priapus,' quoth I, 'help thou the part whose very counterpart, O Sire, thou seemest; and if thou shalt restore it safely to health without amputation,<note type="footnote"> Reminding one of Don Juan's healthy horror when they proposed to circumcise him.</note> I will consecrate to thee, painted on a tablet, a very facsimile of it, alike in size, shape and colour! 'The God promised; for nod bobbed his mentule;<note type="footnote"> Parodying the majestic nod of Jupiter when grating a request.</note> and has granted my prayer.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="38"><p>Since my nature<note type="footnote"> In the original Latin, natura, punningly used in the double sense 'native character' and 'privy part'.</note> is always open, it behoves me to say to thee--whate'er it is--frankly. I wish to pedicate; thou wishest to pluck apples. What I desire, if thou wilt give: what thou desirest, thou shalt receive.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="39"><p>Mercury has a pleasing form, Apollo's is eminent for its beauty; Lyaeus too is painted of comely figure; Cupid is handsomest of all. My figure is, I confess, wanting in beauty, but my mentule is, in truth, magnificent; and if there be a girl with a sensible coynte, she had rather have that for herself than all the former gods</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="40"><p>Telethusa, notorious amongst the damsels of the Via Subura,<note type="footnote"> The Via Subura was a street in Rome, in the second region, under the eastern wall of the Carinae, at the foot of the Coelian Hill, where provisions were chiefly sold, and where many thieves and prostitutes dwelt. Martial writes, of Subura: 'Then hand over the tyro to a Suburan mistress in the art. She will make a man of him; but a virgin is an inexperienced teacher.' And: 'A young lady of not over good reputation, such as sit in the middle of the Subura.'</note> who, I believe, has bought her freedom with the profits of prostitution,<note type="footnote"> For the female slaves to gain their freedom by prostitution was not uncommon. Plautus writes: 'You will speedily be free if you will often lie on your dowry in the same manner. Plautus attributes this to the Tuscans, Augustus to the Phoenicians, Justinus to the Cyprians and Strabo to the Armenians. Herodotus under Clio states that the women of Lydia prostituted themselves to obtain their marriage portion, and that it was a custom amongst the Babylonians that every woman should once in her life prostitute herself at the temple of Venus to a stranger. This practice is confirmed by Jeremiah and Strabo; The prostitution of women, considered as a religious institution, was not only practised in Babylon, but at Heliopolis; at Aphace, a place betwixt Heliopolis and Biblus; at Sicca Veneria, in Africa, and also on the Isle of Cyprus. It was at Aphace that Venus was supposed, according to the author of the Etymologicum Magnum, to have first received the embraces of Adonis. At Argalae, in Africa, women were prostituted on the wedding night. The Loricans, when hard pressed in war, vowed to offer up their daughters to be deflowered in a festival in honour of Venus, if they should be victorious. The Marquis de Sade in his priapistic book La Philsophie dans le Boudoir states Babylonian children were deflowered at the temple of Venus at an early age; and gives some curious details on the subject of prostitution in Pegu and Tartary.</note> encircles thy penis, O venerable one, with a golden crown, for these pathic women consider it equal in eminence to a god.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="41"><p>Whoever comes hither let him become a poet and dedicate to me jocose verses. He who does not, shall, teeming with piles,<note type="footnote"> Piles were a frequent result of sodomy. The word ficus means primarily a fig, and piles were so called from their resemblance in shape to that fruit.</note> walk amongst learned poets.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="42"><p>The steward Aristagoras, rejoicing in his promising grapes, offers to thee, O God, apples formed from wax. Do thou, O Priapus, contented with the semblance of a votive apple, cause him to bear genuine fruit</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="43"><p>Think not that everything I say is spoken in jest and for my own amusement. That ye may not be in doubt, I tell ye this, that all thieves who are often caught I shall irrumate.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="44"><p>What dost thou say this spear, although I be wooden, is wishing, if any girl give kisses to my middle? It needs no soothsayer, for, believe me, she has said, 'The rude spear will exercise its true functions on me.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="45"><p>When the Rigid God beheld an effeminate crisping his hair with the heated curling-irons, to liken himself to a Moorish damsel, 'Ho there, thou catamite,' quoth he. 'We tell thee, thou mayst crisp and curl to thy liking, but is a girl, prithee, of more value than are the hairs which deck thy mentule?'<note type="footnote"> Is it worthwhile disturbing a hair even on thy mentule, much less thy head, to take the semblance of a girl?</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="46"><p>O Damsel, no fairer-skinned than the Moor, but limper than any catamite, briefer in stature than the Pygmies timorous of the crane, harsher in aspect and shaggier than a she-bear, roomier [in thy vulva] than the trousers of the Medes and Indians, thou mayst tarry here or depart at thy will. For, though I may seem fully equipped, 'twould be the work of ten handfuls of rockets* to [induce me to] scrub through the ditches 'twixt thy thighs, and bethwack the worms swarming in thy coynte!</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="47"><p>Whichever of you, who, coming to my banquet, abstains from inscribing to me any verses, I pray that his wife or mistress may make languid his rival with lascivious sporting, whilst he himself sleeps alone through the weary night, excited by lustful rockets.<note type="footnote"> Rocket which he had eaten at supper.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="48"><p>Altho' you see that part of me to be wet by which I'm signified to be Priapus, 'tis not dew, believe me, nor hoarfrost, but what is wont to gush forth spontaneously when my mind recalls a pathic girl [catamite]</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="49"><p>Thou who seest the walls of my temple covered round with jocose poems, not too chaste, cease to be shocked at the obscene verses: mine is not a mentule with raised eyebrow</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="50"><p>If it like thee, O Priapus, a certain girl, most sorely troubled with the piles, sports with me, and neither gives me nor denies her favours, but hitherto has found pretexts for deferring. If it shall to my lot to enjoy her, we will encircle the whole of thy mentule, O Priapus, with our twin garlands</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="51"><p>What is this? Or wherefore do I suspect the greatest number of thieves to come into my garden, when everyone of them who happens unexpectedly upon me pays the penalty and is excavated up to his undulating loins? The fig tree here is no better than my neighbour is, nor are the grapes such as golden-haired Arete<note type="footnote"> The wife of Alcinous, King of the Phaeacians.</note> gathered; nor are the apples meet to be the produce of the trees of Picenum. Neither is the pear, which at such hazard you try to pilfer; nor the plum, more mellow in colour than new wax, nor the service-apple which stays slippery stomachs. Neither do my branches yield an excellent mulberry, the oblong nut, hight filbert, nor the almond bright with purple blossom. I do not, more gluttonously, grow divers kind of cabbage and beet, larger than any other garden trains, and the scallion with its ever-growing head; nor think I that any come for the seed-abounding gourd, the clover, the cucumbers extended along the soil, or the dwarfish lettuce. Nor that any bear away in the night-time lust-exciting rockets, and fragrant mint with healthy rue, pungent onions and fibrous garlic. All of which, though enclosed within my hedgerow, grow with no sparser measure in the neighbouring garden, which having left, ye come to the place which I cultivate, O most vile thieves. Without doubt, ye flock to the open punishment,<note type="footnote"> So called because the natural parts of Priapus were always exposed to view.</note> and the very thing with which I threaten, allures you.<note type="footnote"> The thieves came for the pleasure of being sodomised, instead of looking on it as a punishment.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="52"><p>Hark ye, thou who scarcely withholdest thy greedy hand from the garden entrusted to me. Now, first the watchman, full of lechery, with alternate entrance and exit, shall make thy passage an open one. Then two shall approach, who stand guard at each side, nobly provided with pensile property. Who, when they have grievously ploughed thee, stretched prostrate, to the same part shall come a rampant little ass, by no means inferior in well-hung pizzle. Wherefore, he who is wise will beware of ill-doing, when he knows that here is so much of the mentule</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="53"><p>Bacchus is wont to be content with a modest cluster from the vine, even when the deep vats can barely contain the must. And when the spacious threshing floors are insufficient for the rich harvest, in Ceres' locks a single garland is wreathed. Do thou also, less potent deity, guided by their greater example, although our offering be only a few apples, take it in good part</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="54"><p>If thou writest E and D then addest a joining line, that which wishes to cleave through the middle of D [thee] will be represented.<note type="footnote"> If you write the letters E D and place a dash between them, thus E-D, a mentule will be represented, which wishes to cleave through the middle of D. The ambiguity is in writing the letter D, instead of the Latin word Te (thee), in the second verse. The shape of the mentule is not strikingly apparent at first sight, but the top and bottom strokes of the letter E may be taken as forming the testicles, whilst the middle stroke of the E, continued by the dash thus E-, represents the mentule itself. The D (Te) stands for the anus to be cleaved by the mentule.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="55"><p>Who could believe ('tis a shameful confession!) that the thieves have even purloined the sickle from my very fingers? nor do the disgrace and loss so much affect me as the well-grounded fears of losing other weapons. Which if I lose, I shall be expatriated; and he formerly thy citizen, O Lampsacus, will become a Gaul.<note type="footnote"> The word Gallus means one born in Gaul, and also an emasculated priest of Cybele. Therefore, were the thieves to steal Priapus's phallus, which was often used as a cudgel against garden robbers, he would become a Gallus. Martial relates that a Tuscan soothsayer whilst sacrificing a goat to Bacchus ordered a rustic who was assisting him to castrate the animal. The haruspex, busily intent on cutting the goat's throat, exposed to his assistant's view an immense hernia of his own, which the countryman seized and cut off by mistake, thus converting the Tuscan into a Gaul (Gallus). The priests of Cybele (who were all castrated) were called Galli from Gallus, a river in Phrygia, which turned to madness those who drank of its waters.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="56"><p>Thou also mockest, O thief, and when threatened, dost stretch out to me the indecent finger!<note type="footnote"> The middle finger. It was called 'infamous', according to some writers, on account of the custom of the Jews, who used to wipe the podex when they suffered from bleeding piles. This is not so. It derived its name from its resemblance to the mentule, and it is used in that sense here. When the middle finger is pointing, the other fingers are turned inside, representing a mentule with its accessories; for which reason it was thus pointedly shown in derision to sodomites. Martial: 'Cestus with tears in his eyes often complains to me, Mamurianus, of being teased with your finger.' In an admirable article on pederasty in The Book of the Thousand Nights and a Night: 'Debauchees had signals like Freemasons whereby they recognised one another. The Greek skematízein was made by closing the hand to represent the scrotum and raising the middle finger as if to feel whether a hen had eggs; hence the Athenians called it catapygon or sodomite and the Romans digitus impudicus or infamis, the 'medical finger' of Rabelais and the Chiromantists--though properly speaking medicus is the third or ring-finger, as shown by the old Chiromantist verses. The modern Italian does the same by inserting the thumb-tip between the index and medius to suggest the clitoris. When the Egyptians wish to represent pederasty, they painted two partridges, who, when bereft of their mates, were supposed to enjoy each other. Pliny supports this statement.The finger was also pointed at people as a mark of simple contempt. Martial: 'He points with the finger, but with the infamous finger.' Persius says, without any obscene afterthought, 'The grandmother cleanses with infamous finger the infant.'</note> Alas, unhappy I! that the thing is but wood which makes me seem fearsome. But no matter, I will charge the lecherous owner of the garden that he may be willing to irrumate the thieves for me.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="57"><p>An old crow, a thing of decay, a very sepulchre, grown rotten through the lapse of generations, who perchance might have been the wet-nurse of Tithonus, of Priam, and of Nestor, or who was an old woman maybe when they were boys, beseeches me that a futterer may not be wanting to her. How if she were now to pray that she may become a girl again? Nevertheless if she hath- money, she is a girl.<note type="footnote"> Suggesting she may obtain a lover if she will pay for him. Martial writes,'Lesbia swears that she has never been futtered gratis. It is true: for when shewants to futter, she is wont to pay.' And,Wouldst thou be wimbled gratis when thou artA wrinkled wretch deformed in every part?O 'tis a thing more than ridiculous:To take a man's full sum, and not pay Use!</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="58"><p>Whatever thief who deceives my faith may he wither away, far from the buttocks of a catamite. And whatso girl who with audacious hand plucks off these apples, may she meet with no futterer</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="59"><p>Know this, lest thou shouldst deny being warned, if thou comest a thief thou wilt go dishonoured</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="60"><l>If as many verses so many apples thou hast dedicated to</l>
                    <l>thee, O Priapus, thou wilt be richer than of yore Alcinous.</l></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="61"><p>Why dost thou vainly complain, O husbandman, that I, once a well-fruited apple tree, have now remained sterile throughout two autumns? 'Tis not old age, as thou imaginest, which tells upon me; nor have I been beaten by a violent hailstorm; nor has an unseasonable wintry blast nipped off the blossoms just breaking forth from the stem. Neither have winds, nor rain, nor droughts, given the apple tree any cause to murmur. The starling, the plundering 'daw, the old crow, the water-loving goose, the thirsty raven, none of these has injured me; but the verses of the most execrable of poetasters which I bear on my grievously overladen branches</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="62"><p>Sleep dogs in safety: Sirius will watch over the garden with his beloved Erigone.<note type="footnote"> Sirius, the Dog Star, Erigone, the constellation Virgo. Icarus, the father of Erigone, having been slain by some intoxicated shepherds, his dog Maera, returning home, drew his daughter by her robe to where her father lay. She hanged herself for grief, and the dog perished of hunger. In compassion, Bacchus raised them to the sides, calling Icarus by the name of Boötes; Erigone the Virgin; and Maera, Canicula, Sirius, 'the Dog Star' or Procyon.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="63"><p>'Tis not enough, O friends, that I have fixed my abode here, where the earth gapes into chinks through the heat of the dog days, and that I daily endure the summer's drought; 'tis not enough that the rains flow down my bosom, that hail-storms beat amongst my bared locks, and that my beard frozen together is stiffened by the ice: 'tis too little that having spent the day in labour, I protract it, sleepless, through a night equally long. Add to this, that the unskilled hands of a rustic have chopped me, the awe-inspiring god with a cudgel, and that, amongst all the gods the lowest deity, I am called the wooden guardian of gourds. A pyramid [the virile member] stretched forth with libidinous vigour joins to these the symbol of shamelessness. Hither a damsel (I had almost added her name) is wont to come with her futterer: who if as many forms as Philaenis narrates she does not experience, she departs raging with unsated lust</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="64"><p>A certain one, more tender than the marrow of a goose, comes hither thieving for love of the punishment. He may steal when he fists, I shall not see him</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="65"><p>This pig, which has crushed the rising lilies with his snout, is sacrificed to thee--a victim warm from the stye. But lest thou shouldst cause the whole herd to be annihilated, O Priapus, bid the gate of thy garden to be closed.<note type="footnote"> The priestesses of Priapus were sometimes represented in marble sculptures as clothed with hides of swine.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="66"><p>Thou who, lest thou behold the virile sip, hence withdrawest, as becomes a maiden of modesty: forsooth, unless what thou fearest to see, in thy bowels to have thou longest</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="67"><p>Let the first syllable of PEnelope be followed by the first of DIdo, the first of CAmus by that of REmus.<note type="footnote"> PE-DI-CA-RE--pedicare, meaning to sodomise.</note> What is made from these thou to me, when caught in my garden, O thief, shalt give; by this punishment thy fault is atoned for.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="68"><p>If I, a rustic, shall seem to say anything unlearnedly, pardon me: I gather not knowledge from books, I gather apples. But, untaught, I have often listened to my master, who constantly reads here, and have learnt by heart the Homeric vocabulary. He calls psolen [the virile member], what we call psoloenta. What we call culum [the fundament], he culeon. And surely, unless an unclean thing be called smerdalos [merde], the mentule of a sodomist is smerdalea</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="69"><p>What? had not the Trojan mentule gladdened the Spartan coynte he would have had no theme for his song.<note type="footnote"> Had not Helen eloped with Paris, Homer would not have written the Iliad. Priapus means that sexual love was the cause of the Trojan War. Horace writes--'For before Helen's time [many</note> If the mentule of the descendant of Tantalus<note type="footnote"> Agamemnon was the great-grandson of Tantalus.</note> had not been of renown, the aged Chryses would have had naught of complaint. The same [mentule] deprived his ally of a tender mistress,<note type="footnote"> In the Trojan War the Greeks, having sacked some of the neighbouring towns and taken captive two beautiful maidens, Chryseis and Briseis, allotted the former to Agamemnon and the latter to Achilles. Chryses, priest of Apollo and father of Chryseis, on being refused his daughter's ransom, invoked a pestilence on the Greeks. Agamemnon was thus compelled to deliver up his captive, but in revenge he seized on Briseis, his comrade Achilles' prize. Achilles, in discontent, thereupon withdrew himself and his forces from the rest of the Greeks.</note> and she whom the grandson of Achilles possessed it desired for itself. Achilles chaunted his woeful dirge to the strains of the Pelethronian lyre, himself more 'rigid' than its strings. His ire, thus aroused, verily unfolds the famous Iliad: this was the origin of that immortal poem. The subject of the other [the Odyssey] is the wandering of the crafty Ulysses. If you would know the truth, love inspired this also. Hence is given [to Ulysses] a root from which a golden blossom springs: which, when called moly [by Homer], moly means mentule.<note type="footnote"> The moly was a fabulous herb said by Homer to have been given by Mercury to Ulysses, as a counter-charm against the spells of the enchantress Circe. According to the writer of this epigram, however, the charm simply consisted in the persuasive powers of Ulysses' mentule, through whose means he subjugated both Circe and Calypso.</note> Whence we read that Circe and Calypso, daughter of Atlas, bore children by the mighty implement of the Dulichian hero; and the daughter of Alcinous [Nausicaa] marvelled that his member could scarcely be covered by a leafy branch. Yet he hastened to his little old woman, and all his thoughts were centred in thy coynte, Penelope. Thou who keepest so chaste that in the meantime thou givest banquets and thine house is filled with futterers. And, that of these thou might'st ascertain which wight was the most vigorous, with these words spoken, thou art asking the nerve-extended crew: 'No man stretched his bow-string<note type="footnote"> Parodying the well-known episode of the slaying of the suitors. By a play upon words nervum is here used in the double sense of 'bow-string' and 'mentule'. Apuleius in his Metamorphoses gives the following description of an amorous encounter between Lucius and Fotis--Again and again we pledged each other, until I, now flushed with wine, restless in mind as in body, and moreover wanton with desire (even slightly wounded on the top of my inguinal organ), having removed my garment, showed to Fotus the impatience of my longing.'Pity me,' I cried, 'and speedily relieve me! For, as you perceive, since I received the first of cruel Cupid's arrows buried in my very vitals I have been intent upon the contest, now eagerly approaching, which you had proclaimed for us, without the intervention of a herald. Look at my bow! its very vigour stretches it, and fearfulness for the battle, [and I dread</note> better than my Ulysses, whether 'twas by reason of his side-muscles or of his skill. Who being dead, do ye now stretch forth yours. Thus shall I see if there be a man like unto him; that that man be mine.' With such a treaty, I could have Pleased thee, Penelope: but at that time I was not yet made.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="70"><p>When the sweetness of the fig shall come into thy mind and thou shalt long to stretch forth thine hand hither, glance mindfully on me, O thief, and calculate what weight of mentule will be voided by thee</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="71"><p>A stranger of small means has made me a laughing stock. He had offered up the libum [a cake], strown with spelt and mingled salt, and, having scattered portions on the fire, straightway departed hence, his offering finished. Thereupon comes hither a neighbour's dog, having, I dare say, made for the fumes of smoke; which animal, having devoured the whole of the libation to the mentule, makes atonement to me by its 'rigidity' through the whole night. But do ye be wary of making any more offerings on this spot lest a pack of starving hounds hasten towards me; and lest, in worshipping me and my power, ye have your custodians irrumated.<note type="footnote"> By such conduct the very watchdogs will be turned into thieves and punished as such by the god.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="72"><p>If thou pilferest the orchards entrusted to my care, that I grieve to lose pleasurable things thou wilt be taught</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="73"><p>O Priapus, faithful protector of orchards, warn off the thieves with thy red-painted amulet</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="74"><p>I am inflexible; if thou shalt steal my large apples, I will give thee the apples of the breeches<note type="footnote"> Apples meaning testicles.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="75"><p>With sidelong glances, O pathic girls, why look ye on me? My mentule stands not erect from my groin. Although 'tis now vigourless and unserviceable wood, 'twill be of use if ye sacrifice at my altar</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="76"><p>Through the middles of lads and girls will my mentule make its way; those bearded 'twill not attack save at the height.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="77"><p>Dodona is sacred to thee, O Jupiter; Samos and Mycenae to Juno; Taenarus and its billowy waters to royal Dis. Pallas guards the Cecropian citadels [Athens]; Pythius [Apollo], Delphi the centre of the world;<note type="footnote"> According to an ancient fable, Jupiter, desirous of finding the centre of the world, sent forth two eagles, one from the east, another from the west, ordering them to fly straight forward. They met at Delphi.</note> the maid of Delos [Diana), Crete and the Cynthian Hills; the Faun [Pan], Maenalus and the Arcadian woods. Rhodes is under the blest protection of the sun god [Apollo]; Gades and the humid Tibur, of Hercules; snowy Cyllene of the god of swiftness [Mercury]; and boiling Lemnos is dearer to the tardy god [Vulcan]. The women of Enna worship Ceres; oystery Cyzicum, the ravished goddess [Proserpine]; Gnidus and Paphos, the lovely Venus. To thee, mortals have devoted Lampsacus.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="78"><p>Although I am now growing old, and my beard and locks whiten with hoary hairs, I am still able to perforate [sodomise] a Tithonus, a Priam, and a Nestor, when caught. Ye see that ye stir up my bile, who continually raise a thick fence, and thus prevent thieves from approaching hither. This is hindering, whilst ye help me; this is not to admit birds to the fowler's snare. The way is blocked up, nor can the prostrate one expiate his crime at the expense of his buttocks. So that I who erstwhile was wont ever and ever and ever to cleave the buttocks of pilferers have had naught of employment this many a day and night. I also suffer punishment enough and more than enough; I flow off in seed, and once lecherous, no longer carry out my life's aim. Who would think of the lutist abstaining from his melody? But, lest I perish from senile decay, pray ye desist from such diligence, nor place a fibula on Priapus</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="79"><p>But may the gods and goddesses deny nourishing food to thy teeth, O neighbouring cunnilinge, through whom my girl, hitherto strong and not false, and who was wont swiftly with untired step to hasten to me, now unfortunate Labdace swears that she can scarce drag her feet along by reason of her ditch</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="80"><p>Priapus, though thou mayst be weighty with turgid fascinum, albeit our poet in his verses has cast this in thy teeth, blush not for it. Thou art not more heavily hung than is that poet of ours.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="81"><p>But the stupid mentule does not rise to a sufficient length nor stand well enough, although if you fondle it, you would think it possible to cause it to swell. Woe is me, its dimensions deceive the eager girls,<note type="footnote"> Scioppius says that the girls approach Priapus attracted by the magnificent dimensions of his mentule, but discover that they are not large enough to accommodate the god.</note> for when in proper condition, there is nothing greater than this mentule. Tydeus was of more service, who, if Homer is to be believed, was warlike in nature, puny in stature. But this strangeness and modesty could but be a loss to me: it is oftener thrust from me.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="82"><p>Whilst there is life, 'tis fitting to hope; do thou, O rustic guardian, be present here; and, O stiff-nerved Priapus, be propitious</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="83"><p>Once a household steward, now the tiller of a little field, I, Perspectus, consecrate these temples to thee, O Priapus. For which kind offices I stipulate (if it be righteous, O holy one) that thou may'st be the assiduous protector of the farm; that if any dishonest fellow shall profane our little field, him thou mayst--But silence! I think thou know'st what follows behind</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="84"><p>What news is this? What does the anger of the gods announce? When in the silent night a lovely boy lay with me hidden in my warm bosom, my desire was quiescent, nor did the sluggish penis courageously raise its senile head. Does it please thee, Priapus? who under the foliage of a tree art wont, thy sacred head circled with the leaves and tendrils of the vine, ruddy to sit with rubicund fascinum. But, O Triphallus, oft fresh flowers with loving care have I wreathed in thy locks; and oft driven off with my shouts an aged raven or an active jackdaw when it would have pecked thy sacred head with its horny bill. Fare thee well, Priapus, I owe thee naught. Farewell, impious forsaker of the privities, thou shalt he in the glebe mouldy with neglect; a savage dog shall continually piss upon thee, or a wild boar rub against thee his side befouled with mire. O cursed father of the penis, to whom my calamity [is due], thou shalt expiate this injury with a severe and pious atonement. Thou canst complain: no tender lad shall yield to thee who on the groaning bed with aiding art shall writhe his mobile buttocks. Nor shall a sportive girl caress thee with her gentle hand, or press against thee her lubricious thigh. A mistress with two teeth is prepared for thee, who can call to mind the time of Romulus; and amid her gloomy loins and loose-stretched hide, covered with frost and full of mould and cobwebs, thy privity shall blockade the entrance. This is the one prepared for thee, that thrice and four times her bottomless ditch may swallow up thy lubricious head. Notwithstanding weak and languid thou liest, thou shalt shag her again and again until, O miserable wretch, thrice and fourfold thou fillest her cavity. And now thy pride shall avail thee naught when thou plungest thy reeling head into the splashing mire. Why is [my yard] inert? doth not its sluggishness displease thee? This once thou mayst deprive it of vigour with impunity. But when that golden boy shall return, at the same time that thou hearest the patter of his foot upon the path, on a sudden let a restless swelling excite my nerves with lust and raise my privy part; nor let it cease to incite more and more until sportive Venus shall have spent my feeble strength</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="85"><p>Priapus, guardian not of a garden nor of the sacred vine but of the little grove from which thou wert born and mayst again be born. I warn thee drive off thievish hands and preserve the wood for thy master's hearth. If this be wanting, remember thou too art wooden</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="86"><p>In spring I am worshipped with roses, in autumn with apples, in summer with corn-wreaths, but winter is one horrid pestilence for me. For I fear the cold, and am apprehensive lest I, a wooden god, should in that season afford a fire for ignorant yokels.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="87"><p>I, O traveller, shaped with rustic art from a dry poplar, guard this little field which thou seest on the left, and the cottage and small garden of its indigent owner, and keep off the greedy hands of the robber. In spring a many-tinted wreath is placed upon me; in summer's heat ruddy grain; [in autumn] a luscious grape cluster with vineshoots, and in the bitter cold the pale-green olive. The tender she-goat bears from my pasture to the town milk-distended udders; the well-fattened lamb from my sheepfolds sends back [its owner] with a heavy handful of money; and the tender calf, 'midst its mother's lowings, sheds its blood before the temple of the gods. Hence, warfarer, thou shalt be in awe of this god, and it will be profitable to thee to keep thy hands off. For a punishment is prepared--a roughly-shaped mentule. 'Truly, I am willing,' thou sayest; then, truly, behold the farmer comes, and that same mentule plucked from my groin will become. an apt cudgel in his strong right hand.<note type="footnote"> The traveller mocks at Priapus's threat of sodomy as a punishment. The god, in anger, retorts that if that punishment has no fears for him, a fustigation by the Farmer with the self-same mentule used as a cudgel may have a more deterrent effect.</note></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="88"><p>This place, youths, and the marshland cot thatched with rushes, osier-twigs and bundles of sedge, I, carved from a dry oak by a rustic axe, now protect, so that they thrive more and more every year. For its owners, the father of the poor hut and his son--both husbandmen--revere me and salute me as a god; the one labouring with assiduous diligence that the harsh weeds and brambles may be kept away from my sanctuary, the other often bringing me small offerings with open hand. On me are placed a many-tinted wreath of early spring flowers and the soft green blade and ear of the tender corn. Saffron coloured violets, the orange-hued poppy, wan gourds, sweet-scented apples, and the purpling grape trained in the shade of the vine [are offered] to me. Sometimes, (but keep silent as to this)<note type="footnote"> Priapus was afraid of the anger of the Celestials if they heard of his receiving honours due to them alone; for he was one of that lower order of deities, to which Faunus, Hippona and others belonged, who were not admitted into heaven or entitled to blood offerings.</note> even the beaded he-goat and the horny-footed nanny sprinkle my altar with blood: for which honours Priapus is bound in return to do everything [which lies in his duty], and to keep strict guard over the little garden and. vineyard of his master. Wherefore, abstain, O lads, from your evil pilfering here. Our next neighbour is rich and his Priapus is negligent. Take from him; this path then will lead you to his grounds.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="89"><p>This grove I dedicate and consecrate to thee, Priapus, who hast thy home at Lampsacus, and eke thy wood lands, Priapus; for thee especially in its cities worships the coast of the Hellespont, richer in oysters<note type="footnote"> Oysters being an incentive to lust. Juvenal writes: 'She knows no difference 'twixt head and privities who devours immense oysters at midnight.'</note> than all other shores.</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="90"><p>Thou who with penis men dost terrify, and with sickle catamites, the acres few of this secluded spot protect. So in thine orchards may enter no aged thieves, but only boy or handsome girl, long-haired</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="91"><p>I am not shaped from the fragile elm, nor is this column of mine which stands extended with rigid vein [made] from wood taken at random, but produced from the evergreen cypress which neither a hundred full-told generations nor the decay of a lengthy senility fears. This do thou, whoever thou mayst be, O ill-doer, dread; for if with greedy hand but the smallest dusters of grapes on this vine thou dost injure, there shall be born on thee, however much thou mayst wish to oppose it, a fig tree grafted from this cypress</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="92"><p>A Cilician thief of but too notorious rapacity wished to rob a certain garden; but large as the garden was, O Fabullus, there was naught in it save a marble Priapus. Not desiring to go back empty-handed, the Cilician stole Priapus himself</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="93"><p>No ignorant peasant shaped me with unskilful sickle: the noble handywork of the steward thou perceivest. For the most influential cultivator of the Caeretan lands, Hilarus, owns these hills and smiling slopes. Behold, with well-shaped features I do not seem to be wooden, nor belly-weapons devoted to the kitchen-fire do I bear; but my imperishable mentule of undying cypress, worthy the hand of Phidias, stiffly raises itself. Neighbours, I warn you, worship the sacred Priapus, and these fourteen acres respect</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="94"><p>If thou desirest to appease thine hunger, thou canst eat our Priapus; thou mayst munch even its privities, thou wilt still be pure</p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="95"><p>Aforetimes I was the trunk of a wild fig tree, useless wood,<note type="footnote"> The wood of a fig tree was very little used, on account of its brittleness.</note> when the craftsman, uncertain whether to make a bench or a Priapus, preferred me to be the god. A god henceforth became I, to the thieves and birds the greatest of bugbears; for my right hand checks pilferers, and a ruddy pole thrust forth from obscene groin; while a cane to my pate affixed alarms the pestering birds, and prevents them from flocking down upon these recently made gardens.<note type="footnote"> Octavius, willing to correct the infection of this hill, which was a common burying-place for all the poor of Rome, got the consent of the senate and people to give part of it to Maecenas, who built a magnificent house there, with very extensive gardens.</note> Hither, of yore, corpses from strait cells expelled, by brother-slaves were conveyed for disposal in mean biers. This for the miserable mob stood a common sepulchre, for Pantolabus the droll and Nomentanus the spendthrift. A thousand feet of frontage, three hundred backwards in field a boundary stone here gave, lest the memorial ground descend to the heirs. Now one may inhabit the Esquiliae made salubrious, and promenade on the terrace 'neath the sun, where but lately the saddened observed the ground distorted by white bones; as for me, nor thieves nor wild beasts wont this place to infest cause so much of trouble and labour as do those females who with magical songs and with venoms do overturn the minds of folk. These in no wise to make away with am I able nor to prevent, soon as the fleeting moon her beauteous visage shows forth, from gathering together dry bones and noisome herbs. With mine own eyes did I see with black garment upgirdled Canidia, walking barefoot and dishevelled of hair, with Sagana the elder a-screeching (and pallor had made both of horrible aspect) begin to claw up the ground with their</p></div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>